<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title/>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<p/>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Created from islandora book ingest unless otherwise noted.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text>
		<front/>
		<body>
			<div xml:id="struct_540">
				<head type="title" xml:id="struct_543">The Legend of the Two Sisters</head>
				<byline xml:id="struct_544">By E. Pauline Johnson &#x2013; Tekahionwake</byline>
				<p xml:id="struct_541">You can see them from the heights, from the <placeName
						xml:id="struct_1797">pleasure grounds</placeName>, from the gay thoroughfares, from the
					great hotel windows - those twin peaks of the twin mountains that lift their pearly
					summits across the inlet which washes with its ceaseless tides the margins of Vancouver,
					the beautiful city which is called 'The Sunset Gateway' of the Dominion of <placeName
						xml:id="struct_1413">Canada</placeName>. Sometimes the smoke of forest fires blurs these
					twin peaks, until they swim in a purple atmosphere too beautiful for words to paint.
					Sometimes the slanting rains festoon their grey and gauzy veils about the crests, and the
					peaks fade into inadequate outlines of soft shadows, melting, melting, <del
						xml:id="struct_2177">forever melting</del>, into the distances. But for most days of the
					year, the sun circles the twin glories with a sweep of gold, the moon washes them with a
					torrent of silver, and they stand immovable through sun and shadow, smiling on one side
					above the waters of the restless Pacific, on the other, above the depths and eternal
					silence of the Capilano Canon. Throughout the British Darn Empire these peaks are known as
					'The Lions of Vancouver.' Their striking resemblance to Landseer's Lions at the base of
					Nelson's Monument in Trafalgar Square, London, has won them this name. But the Indians of
					the coast know nothing of the white man's appellation, and you must indeed get near to the
					heart of some ancient Klootchman before she will consent to tell you the Legend of the
					Twin Sisters.&#xA0;</p>
				<p xml:id="struct_542">We had been driving for some time, the handsome chief of the
					Capilanos sitting in the front seat of the light surrey, his slim, silent young daughter
					beside him, I in the back seat, and at my side the quaint old Indian mother, who, from
					time to time, told me the traditions of her people, in the half-halting broken English
					that is never so beautiful as when it slips from an Indian tongue. At our feet were
					baskets of exquisite weaver, all her handiwork, and that of her young daughter sitting
					before us. With housewifely care she had stowed these away before starting for the drive,
					for it was berry time, and she had no thought of leaving such precious muck-a-muck for the
					foxes and birds, when her children and grandchildren had willing mouths to be filled. The
					chief was an excellent provider, but 'Why not add to the store?' she remarked simply. 'One
					must not be wasteful of these precious, God-given wild things.' So the baskets reposed
					nearby, ready to be filled when opportunity afforded. The trail wound about the foot of a
					cluster of mountains, following a riotous stream called the Capilano River, which brawled
					and quarrelled, whispered and laughed among its rocks and boulders, tumbling head-long one
					moment, the next circling into a deep, transparent pool where leaping salmon and shy
					mountain trout glinted in the sunshine. 'So many things belong to this river,' said the
					Klootchman in her pretty, stammering English, which I must eliminate if I am to make this
					story lucid. So I must keep to the everyday phrases, and my readers must be the losers of
					her fascinating expressions; but after all, it was her wonderful eyes and gestures that
					really made the tale, and what use to attempt a description of these? It is impossible.
					'Yes, the river holds many secrets,' she continued, 'secrets of strong men's battles and
					many tragedies, but the mountains hold the secrets of an Indian mother's heart, and those
					are the greatest secrets of all things.' Her voice fell to a whisper, but her speaking
					eyes swept the distant summits with an understanding far subtler than sight. I did not
					offer a reply, for I knew that in her own good time the Klootchman would catch the mood of
					the mountains and impart to me some of their lore. The silence was long. Once or twice she
					swept effective gestures that were filled with meaning. She wishes me to notice the crags
					and ledges, haunts of the mountain sheep and wild goats, a winging hawk, a leaping trout,
					the crimsoning o-lil-lies (Chinook for berries). Then as if from dreams she suddenly
					awoke. 'You will want to know the secret that is held in the mountains, the secret of the
					Indian mother's heart?' she asked. I nodded. I could see she liked that wordless reply,
					for she placed her narrow brown hand on my arm, nor did she remove it during her entire
					recital of The Legend of the Two Sisters'You see them - those two peaks - towering forever
					and ever in that high place? Those are the Chief's Daughters, that every Indian mother
					loves. You see them, but you may not know - you who have come from the Land of Morning,
					the Land of Sunrise - for you have different customs, different traditions, from those of
					our people in the Sunset Land. I say you may not know that when our daughters step from
					childhood into the great world of womanhood, when the fitness for motherhood crowns them,
					we coast Indians of the sunset country regard this occasion as one of extreme rejoicing,
					great honour and unspeakable gladness. The being who possesses the possibility of some day
					becoming a mother receives much honour in most nations, but to us, the Sunset Tribes of
					Redmen, she is almost sacred. So, when our girls reach womanhood, we make it a great
					occasion. The parents usually give a feast that lasts many days. The entire tribe is
					bidden to this festival. More than that, when a great Tyee (Chinook for chief) celebrates
					for his daughter, sometimes the tribes from far up the coast, from the far North, from
					inland, from the mountain passes, and the Cariboo Country, are bidden as guests to the
					feast. During these feast days the girl is placed in a high seat, an exalted position, for
					is she not marriageable? and does not marriage mean motherhood? and is not motherhood the
					most exalted position in the world? So we place the girl on a high elevation, for she must
					know and realize her responsibility, she must recognize that she is the greatest factor in
					the world, and she must sit in a high place as becomes her heritage as a woman, therefore
					as a possible mother, for this is the law of our people - we of the Sunset Tribes. It was
					years ago, hundreds of years - yes, thousands of years (the sweet old Klootchman
					pronounced it 'Tousen off yea-rs.' It was the only sentence of her quaint, broken English
					I was ever able to actually capture) - yes, more than thousands of years ago that the
					great Tyee of our tribe had two daughters, young, livable, and oh! very beautiful. They
					grew to womanhood the same time, and a mighty feast was to be given, such a feast as the
					Coast had never yet seen. The only shadow on the joy of it all was war, for the tribe of
					the great Tyee was at war with the Upper Coast Indians - those who lived north of what is
					now named by the white men the Port of Prince Rupert.'Giant war canoes fretted the entire
					coast line, war parties paddled their way up and down, war songs broke the silences of the
					nights, strife, hatred, vengeance festered everywhere, like sores on the surface of the
					earth. But the great Tyee snatched a week away from the bloodshed and battle, for he must
					make this feast in his daughter's honour, nor permit any mere enemy to come between him
					and the traditions of his race and household. So her turned deaf ears to their war songs,
					he ignored their insulting paddle-dips, which encroached within his own coast waters, and
					he prepared, as a great Tyee should, to celebrate in honour of his daughters. 'But five
					suns before the feast these two maidens came to him, hand within hand. "Some day we may
					mother a man-child," they said, "a man-child who may grow to be just such a great Tyee as
					you are, oh, our father, and for this honour that may some day be ours, we have come to
					crave a favour of you." '"What favour, children of mine, and of your mother? It is yours
					for the asking, this day," he answered. "Will you, for our sakes, invite the hostile
					tribe, the tribe you war upon, to our feast?" they asked. "To a peaceful feast, a feast in
					the honour of women?" he exclaimed. "So we would have it," they replied. "And so shall it
					be," he declared. "I can deny you nothing this day, and sometime your sons may be born to
					bless this peace you have asked, and to bless their mothers' sire for giving it."'Then he
					turned to the young men of the tribe and said, "Build fires this night on all the coast
					headlines, fires of welcome. Go forth in your canoes, face the north, and greet the enemy,
					and tell them that I, the Tyee of the Capilanos, bid them join me for a feast in honour of
					my two daughters."'And when the Northern tribes got the invitation they flocked down the
					coast to this feast of a great Peace. They brought their women and their children, they
					brought game and fish and o-lil-lie, as gifts. Never was such a Potlatch (a gift feast),
					never was such joyousness, such long, glad days, such soft, sweet nights. The war canoes
					were emptied of deadly weapons and filled with the daily catch of salmon. The hostile war
					songs ceased, and in their place were heard laughter and singing, and the play-games of
					the children of two tribes which had been until now ancient enemies, and a great and
					lasting brotherhood was sealed between them. The war songs were ended forever.' The
					Klootchman's voice fell very low, and the last words were almost whispered. 'And what of
					the two sweet daughters of the great Tyee?' I asked, slipping my hand in hers. 'They are
					there,' she said, pointing to the twin peaks which rose far above us. 'The Great Spirit
					made them immortal. They will always be there in that high place. Their offspring now rule
					these tribes, for were not Peace and Brotherhood born of them? And there the two Sisters
					have stood these thousands of years, and will stand for thousands of years to come,
					guarding the Peace of the Pacific coast, and the serenity of the Capilano Canon.'</p>
			</div>
			<ab>ood, when the &#xFB01;tness for motherhood crowns<lb/>e coast Indians of the sunset
				country regard this<lb/>as one of extreme rejoicing, great honor and<lb/>ble gladness. The
				being who possesses the pos&#x2014;<lb/>of some day hecoming a mother receives much<lb/>in
				most nations, but to us, the Sunset Tribes of<lb/>she is almost sacred. So, when our girls
				reach<lb/>- d, we make it a great occasion. The parents<lb/>y give a feast that lasts many
				days. The entire<lb/>&#x2018;is bidden to this festival. More than that. when a<lb/>Tyce
				(Chinook for chief) celebrates for his daughter,<lb/>times the tribes from far up the coast,
				from the far<lb/>from inland, from the mountain pa -es. and the<lb/><lb/>&#x2019; boo
				Country, are bidden as guests to the feast. During<lb/>feast days the girl is placed in a
				high seat, an exalted<lb/>tion, for is 'le not nlarriageable? and does not mar&#xBB;<lb/>g ,
				mean motherhood? and is not motherhood the most<lb/>&#xAB; ted position in the world? So we
				place the girl on a<lb/>j elevation, for she must know and realize her
				responsi&#x2014;<lb/>lty, she must recognize that she is the greatest factor<lb/>_ the
				world, and she must sit in a high place as becomes<lb/>heritage as a woman, therefore as a
				possible mother,<lb/>: this is the law of our pe0ple&#x2014;we of the Sunset Tribes.<lb/>'
				was years ago, hundreds of years&#x2014;yes, thousands of years<lb/>i e sweet old Klootchman
				pronounced it "Tousen o&#xFB01;<lb/>-rs." It was the only sentence of her quaint,
				broken<lb/>glish I was ever able to actually capture)&#x2014;yes, more<lb/>thousands of
				years ago that the great Tyee of our tribe<lb/><lb/>, d two daughters. young, lovable, and
				oh! very beau&#xBB;<lb/>_ ful. They grew to wom-<lb/>hood the same time. autl<lb/>mighty
				feast was to he<lb/>ven, such a feast as the<lb/>. st had never yet seen.<lb/>A e only
				shadow on the joy<lb/>f it all was war, for the<lb/>- ibe of the great Tyee<lb/>as at war
				with the Upper<lb/>Coast ln(liali~ihose who<lb/>,lived north of wllat is now<lb/>med by the
				white men<lb/>&#x2018;the Port of Prince Rupert.<lb/>' &#x201C;Giant war canoes
				fret-<lb/>ted the entire coast line,<lb/>war parties |):|ll(.llE(l their<lb/>&#x2018;way up
				and down, war ,<lb/>mugs broke the silences of &gt;<lb/>the nights, strife, hatred,
				-<lb/>vengeance festered every-<lb/>where, like sores on the<lb/>surface of the earth.
				But<lb/>The great Tyee snatched a<lb/><lb/>i<lb/><lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/><lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/><lb/>.daughters' honor, nor per<lb/>&#x2018;init any mere enemy to<lb/>come between him
				and the<lb/>&#x201C;traditions of his race and<lb/>household. So he tnrlletl<lb/>deaf ears
				to their war<lb/>tsougs, he ignored their IlI&#x2014;<lb/>suiting parldle-dips,
				which<lb/>,encroachcrl within his own<lb/><lb/>
				<lb/><lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/><lb/>it who: favor, cmltlren 0/ mlne! 1: in yours Iur the nmag ma
				day.&#x201D;<lb/><lb/>coast waters, and he prepared, as a great Tyee should,
				to<lb/>celebrate in honor of his daughters. -<lb/><lb/>"But live suns before the feast these
				two maidus came<lb/>to him, hand within hand. &#x2018; Some day we may nglrtber
				I<lb/>nian~chiltl,' they said, &#x2018;a manrchild who may to be<lb/>just such a great Tyee
				as you are, oh, our father, |_nd bar<lb/>this honor that may some day be ours, we have come
				to<lb/>crave a favor of you.&#x2018;<lb/><lb/>&#x201C; ' What favor, children of mine, and
				of your mnlher?<lb/>It is yours for the asking, this day,&#x2019; he
				answered.<lb/><lb/>&#x201C;Will you, for our sakes, invite the hostile tribe, the<lb/>tribe
				you war upon, to our feast?&#x2018; they asked.<lb/><lb/>&#x2018;&#x201C;To a peaceful
				feast, a feast in the honor of women?&#x2019;<lb/>he exclaimed.<lb/><lb/>~ &#x2018; So we
				would have it,&#x2019; they replied.<lb/><lb/>&#x201C; l .-\nd so shall it be,&#x2019; he
				declared &#x2018;I can deny you n0t|I~<lb/>ing this day. and sometime your sons may be born
				to bless<lb/>this peace you have asked. and to bless their mothers&#x2018; sire<lb/>for
				iving it.&#x2019;<lb/><lb/>&#x2018;hen he turned to the young men of the tribe and<lb/>said,
				&#x2018; Build &#xFB01;res this night on all the coast headlines, &#xFB01;res<lb/>of
				welcome. Go forth in your canoes, face the north, and<lb/>greet the enemy, and tell them
				that 1, the Tye&#xE9; of the<lb/>capilanos, bid them join me for a (east in honor of
				my<lb/>two daughters.&#x2019;<lb/><lb/>&#x201C;And when the Northern tribes got that
				invitation they<lb/>&#xFB02;ocked down the coast to this feast of a great Peace.
				They<lb/>brought their women and their children, they brought game<lb/>and fish alltl
				o&#x2014;l.il- e, as gifts. Never was such a Potlatch<lb/>(a gift feast), never was such
				joyousncss, such<lb/>lung, glad days, such soft. sweet nights. The war<lb/>canoes were
				emptied of deadly weapons and filled<lb/>with the daily catch of salmon. The hostile
				war<lb/>songs ceased, and in their place were heard laughter<lb/>and singing, and the
				play&#x2014;games of the children<lb/>of two tribes which had been until now
				ancient<lb/>enemies, and a great and lasting brotherhood<lb/>was sealed between them. The
				war<lb/>songs were ended forever."<lb/><lb/>
				<lb/><lb/>The Klomchman&#x2019;s voice fell very<lb/>low, and the last words were
				almost<lb/>whispered.<lb/><lb/>"And what of the two sweet daugh&#xBB;<lb/><lb/>ters of the
				great Tyec ?" I asked,<lb/>slipping my hand in hers.<lb/><lb/>" They are there," she said,
				point-<lb/>ing to the twin peaks<lb/>which rose far above us.<lb/>"The Great Spirit
				made<lb/>them immortal. They will<lb/>always he there in that<lb/><lb/>- week away from
				bloodshed high place. Their on. '<lb/>and battle, for he must spring now rule
				these<lb/>.make this feast in his tribes, for were not Peace<lb/><lb/>and Brotherhood bom
				of<lb/>them? And there the Two<lb/>Sisters have stood these<lb/>thousands of years,
				and<lb/>will stand for thousands of<lb/>years [0 come, guarding<lb/>the Peace of the
				Paci&#xFB01;c<lb/>coast, and the sere of<lb/>the Capilano Ca&#xFB01;on.&#x201D;<lb/><lb/>
				<lb/><lb/>
				<lb/><lb/>
				<lb/><lb/>&#x201C; lvlllc habit of obedience, fort-ed in upon the
				imnressihle<lb/><lb/>&#x2018;nature of a child, (I09)! not develop judgment am!<lb/>will,
				but does develop that fntul facility in following other<lb/>people&#x2018;: judgment and
				other people&#x2019;: wills which tends to<lb/>make us 1 helpless mob, more sheep. inxlend
				of wise. free,<lb/>slrong individuals. The bllhit of lilllml&#x2018; 'on to
				authority,<lb/>the long. l&#x2018;lcepl_ mprelued t&#x2018;0l\Vl('tl0n that to be good is
				to<lb/>give up, that there is virtue in the act of surrenderrihis in<lb/>one of the sources
				from which we cnntinllally replenish<lb/>bllmun wenlmenu, &#xFB01;nd &#xFB01;ll the world
				with an inert Inusn of<lb/>mindleutl, willrlesx folk, pushed and pulled about by
				those<lb/>whom they obey.<lb/><lb/>
				<lb/><lb/>
				<lb/>
				<lb/><lb/>&#x2018;Moreover, there is the opposite elrect&#x2014;the injurious<lb/>rt-at-lion
				rroro ob&lt;=lIiencw=&#x2014;nlmolot as common and hurttul :5<lb/>its full roltievernent;
				namely, that &#xFB01;erce, rebellious desire to<lb/>do eriir-tly the oppoirite of whul one
				is told. which is no<lb/>nein-er to calm judgment than the other.<lb/><lb/>"In obeying
				another will or in resisting another will. '<lb/>nothing is gained in wisdom. A hunnin
				creature in a sole<lb/>gov-ernin,v intelligence, and the rich years of childhood<lb/>should
				be passed in the guarded exercise of those powers.<lb/><lb/>~ It is a commonplace
				observation that the beat children,<lb/>i. e., the most submislive and obedient, do not
				nnrlre the but<lb/>men."&#x2014;&#x2014;&#x201C; vanmnmg !'hildren," ailrrnrn.<lb/><lb/>M .n
				lA\' </ab>
		</body>
		<back/>
	</text>
</TEI>
